When the British army liberated Bergen
[music] Belson,
I was amongst the dead. I was a
skeleton.
So they [music] dumped me on the truck
to be taken care of.
And in the [music] last minute,
one of the officers passed by. He pulled
my leg that was hanging out,
took my pulse,
and [music] he said, "That skeleton is
still alive.
At the end of the war, the whole camp
was full of corpses.
The Nazis, they didn't know who was
alive, who was dead. If they thought
that you were alive, they'd shoot you.
My mother, she hid me with a corpse.
As she covered me up, she said, "You're
not going to move and you're going to
breathe into the floor." She said,
My job was to get into the camps [music]
as quickly as they were liberated.
I had peered into hell.
They unlocked [music] the gates and then
they took pictures of us.
I have a a pretty good [music] picture
with my number showing
>> the survivors.
They walked away with only a tattoo on
their arm.
Everything they had owned was gone,
including their [music] families.
Where [music] was the money to come from
to heal them?
to house them,
to allow them to begin their new lives.
The needs of the survivors were as great
as they were urgent.
Two states who go to war, the state that
wins exacts reparations from the state
that loses. Reparations have existed
since time immemorial. But the idea of
compensation to individuals was
unprecedented.
>> How is Germany going to pay [music] for
this?
We had bombed the hell out of Germany
>> in 1952.
The German population was the same
population that [music] committed that
what happened during the warn
>> for the Israelis. It was really a
[music] dramatic change to begin a
conversation with the representatives of
Germany. It was for them like
negotiating with the devil.
Blood bunny. I always called it blood
money.
There was this bomb being sent to the
German chancellor and there were other
bombs being sent to the delegations in
Vasina.
There was a terrorist group which was
out [music] to kill me and to kill all
the others
who dares to simply [music] the Germans
to talk about how much they owe for my
parents.
I don't know what happened [music] to my
parents and my sister. And every night
when I go to [music] sleep, I say, "My
papa, where are you? Where are you?
Where is [music] my family? Why am I
alone?
I don't have anybody. I'm still a
[music] child."
One Jewish negotiator said he felt the
souls of 6 million Jews in the room with
him that day.
At Bimar, all citizens were ordered to
visit the concentration [music] camp.
They were forced to see with their own
eyes crimes whose existence they had
indignantly denied.
They tell you now that they knew nothing
of what was going on or could do nothing
even if they knew.
>> The Germans had for 12 years been
[music] indoctrinated
that the Jews were a danger to their
existence.
They didn't really understand why they
had to pay compensation.
One has to see that everybody, even
those who had been on the other side
against the Nazis, they were not willing
to deal with [music] the crimes.
Everybody was rejecting the notion of
collective guilt.
We mention
Fore about
[music]
the allies conducted a number of polls
amongst the Germans. Who did they
consider to be the main victims of the
war?
Jews always ranked at the bottom.
They were so preoccupied with building
up [music] their lives.
Only 11% of the German population
supported compensation talks.
Focus.
for
Israel.
He said that of course this compensation
this reparation is also in [music] a way
accepting German guilt.
>> [music]
>> In 1949, West Germany became a new
sovereign nation, the Federal Republic
of Germany with Conrad Adenau as its
chancellor. East Germany was behind the
Iron Curtain, cut off from the West.
As the first chancellor, he had the task
of rebuilding West Germany as a
democracy,
regaining membership among the civilized
nations of the world, and restoring
[music]
the good name of Germany.
He was a devout Catholic and had been
opposed to Nazism. His family had paid a
severe price for their opposition.
These are the German usal pictures put
out following the attempt on a furious
life. Conjecture runs high as
for
since done here.
forch.
[music]
for
dry
in Foreign
speech. Foreign speech. Foreign speech.
Adnau faced fierce opposition to the
idea of paying reparations even within
his own cabinet. The biggest threat to
Adenau's plans was finance minister
Fritz Schaefer.
>> Schaefer thought that maybe the German
Federal Republic is not capable of
bearing that financial burden. I mean, I
wouldn't call him an anti-semite, but he
thought that if Israel needs money,
Israel should address maybe the United
States or others for a credit.
And he had a very important position in
the German cabinet. He has the right to
veto.
So, it was very important for Adenau to
overcome that.
The speech by Adenau was received by the
world as a a very brave speech
but not in Israel.
>> We hereby proclaim the establishment of
the Jewish state in Palestine to be
called the state of Israel.
>> Like Adenau, Bengurian was building a
new nation out of the ashes. The two
leaders actually had a great deal in
common. Both men were unique
combinations of moralists and realists.
>> The lesson that Benuan took from the
Holocaust, it was that we, the Jews,
need to protect themselves. No one saved
the Jews.
They can't wait for other nations to
protect them. And if the Jews want to
save themselves, they need weapons.
For weapons, you need money. And no one
is not going to give it to us.
This evening, the invasion. Arab armies
are pouring in. Their tanks have already
crossed the borders, and the frontier
settlements have helped the first
onslaught of the fighting forces of the
organized Arab armies.
>> The Israel War of Independence was the
longest and the most dire in the history
of the Jewish state.
about 85%
gross national product was devoted to
finance this war.
In the midst of the war, Israel opened
its gates for a wave of mass Jewish
[music] immigrations.
About 700,000
Jewish immigrants came to Israel,
absorbed by a population of 600,000
Jews.
This figure is an unprecedented in the
history of of nations.
Half of the immigrants came from Arab
Muslim worlds
and half of the immigrants came from
Europe. There were Holocaust survivor.
In June 1950,
Israel had about $65 [music]
million.
At the end of 1951,
the Israel treasury was empty.
Collapse of the economy is virtually the
collapse of the state itself.
Ben Gurion, he knew that for the
survival
of Israel, Israel must obtain this
reparations.
It was a very difficult decision.
He locked himself into a psychological
mood of not listening to the criticism
because he says I cannot judge or
comment on the pain of my brothers and
sisters who went through the Holocaust.
But now I have to do whatever I can to
build a nation to move forward.
Ever since the full and horrific extent
of the Holocaust was discovered,
kind of spontaneous popular boycott was
imposed in Israel on Germany.
This boycott was the expression of the
sense of revolution,
feelings of hatred,
the desire for revenge.
There was a complete rejection of
everything German,
not only the Nazis,
German art,
German music,
the German language,
even German [music] products.
That is an Israeli passport that can be
used for every country
and here
except Germany.
I have written the excerpt of Sharet
speech at the
Jews were killed but the German people
continues to enjoy the spoils of the
slaughter and pillage perated by the
previous leaders.
of this we can say hast thou killed and
also taken possession.
A member of David Bengorian's party
during the debate rose and said, "You're
a traitor to the Jewish people.
Even if you sign an agreement with the
Germans, they'll never pay. They're
going to make fools of you."
The emotion was very high in the but it
was nothing compared to the atmosphere
outside the streets.
>> [music]
[music]
>> The prominent leader that execute this
demonstration was Man, an Holocaust
survivor.
When man begging end his speech, stones
were thrown against the police officers
and some members of theet were injured.
This was actually the first time and the
last time in [music] Israel history that
the Nesset was stormed.
>> [music]
>> The motion to approve negotiations with
the German people passed,
but only by a single vote.
The foreign office decided on a 1
[music] billion claim. The claim was
based on the cost for absorbing 500,000
broken survivors.
But Adnau had offered to negotiate with
Israel and a representative of world
jury. It was just one small detail.
No such organization existed.
The Jewish people were fragmented. They
were divided. They had a multiplicity
[music] of organizations.
How do you bring them together to speak
in one voice?
>> If the leaders of the democratic peoples
of the last decade would have had just a
little bit more of common sense, just a
little bit more of moral courage, this
second cold war would have been easily
avoidable.
Malakim Goldman was the only leader at
the time who had the gravitas, who had
the influence to corral politically and
religiously diverse Jewish [music]
leaders from around the world.
Goldman was stripped of his German
citizenship by the Nuremberg laws of
1935 and he was forced to leave Germany
that very same year. He became deeply
involved in Jewish affairs. He was
president of the agency for Palestine,
basically the governing body of the
pre-state Jewish community in Israel.
And he was a founder and president of
the World Jewish Congress.
One month after Adaua speech, Dah
Goldman sent out invitations in the name
of the Jewish Agency to 23 organizations
and it was arranged very quickly. They
all got together in the Waldorf Histori
in New York.
He did bring together a fairly wide
range of organizations.
>> The first big question was who
represents the victims.
There were survivors in Israel, but
there were survivors all over the world.
In the early 1950s, there were still
tens of thousands of Holocaust survivors
who were living in the DP camps.
They didn't have bank accounts. [music]
They didn't have homes to go back to.
They didn't inherit anything from their
parents who had been murdered.
And they were deprived of an education.
>> Israel's [music] representative to the
United Nations, Aba Iben, came to the
meeting in New York. His main argument
was that Israel should represent all
Holocaust survivors worldwide.
The other delegates refused to accept
his position. They rejected the idea
that Israel should monopolize.
Monopolize is the word they use.
Monopolize the claims. [music]
>> That's not going to fly. The diaspora
organizations also had ongoing needs in
looking after Holocaust [music]
survivors. And there was the whole
question of rehabilitating the
devastated [music] Jewish communities in
Europe.
On the second day of the meeting, a vote
was taken to create the organization.
One group that was vehemently opposed
was Agurat Israel, the representative
[music] Orthodox jury. The spokesman for
a good Israel said the Jewish world
would commit moral suicide if the offer
of Adenau was not immediately rejected.
The vote was 22 to1 in favor and thus
the conference on Jewish material claims
against Germany. [music] The claims
conference was formed.
They decided to insert into our already
unwieldy name the word material because
they wanted the world [music] to
understand this was about material
reparations.
But the issues of morality
of justice
those would not be solved [music] or
closed by a negotiation.
The nason claims conference had to
figure out on what legal [music] basis
they would present claims.
There was no precedent for what they
were trying to achieve in international
law.
Fortunately, the claims conference had
pulled in a handful of brilliant
lawyers.
We ask this court to affirm by
international penal action
man's right to live in peace and dignity
regardless of his race or creed.
>> When I was still a student at the
Harvard Law School, the first year class
taught me that if you do harm to
someone, a wrongful act, you have an
obligation to try to make amends.
Fundamental principle of law had nothing
to do with Nazis, nothing to do with
Germany. It had to do with law and
morality.
>> He had been drafted into the army right
out of law school and had never tried a
case. Nevertheless, he was tapped to be
the lead prosecutor in the Nerburgg
trials of the SS mobile killing squads
who had murdered some 2 million men,
women, and children.
>> The case we present is a plea of
humanity to law.
Finding the theory was the first
obstacle.
How do you frame it and what form of a
war and under which headings?
We decided very early on we're not going
to ask for [music] anything for loss of
life.
It was too difficult for us to [music]
say
grandpa was worth more than grandma
or you're worth more [music] than
somebody else who was killed.
The most important basis [music] for
individual survivor claims against
Germany was personal suffering. What
happened to [music] that particular
Holocaust survivor? What they endured?
Where were they? Were they in camps?
Were they in ghettos for what period of
time?
And there was a second claim which was
based on the value of the property that
had been plundered by the Nazis and for
which there had been no claims because
there were [music] no surviving owners.
>> The Holocaust was not only a war against
the Jewish people. It was the biggest
asset stripping operation in history.
Whole families were completely
annihilated
and suddenly there was property but
there were no propriators anymore. Who
is going to claim that property?
It cannot happen. That property will
become legal property in the land where
that that crimes were committed. [music]
you have murdered and now you are going
to appropriate
the means of the murdered that cannot
happen that's morally unacceptable in
any culture of [music] the world
the idea was that the German [music]
compensation would assist survivors to
rebuild their lives
but this did not [music] constitute in
itself an acknowledgement of the fact
that Jews forgave forgave the Germans
because the Jews didn't forgive the
Germans.
After liberation, we were going back to
our hometown Tomas of Mazavetski
where my grandparents,
great-grandparents,
200 years of people were born there and
lived there.
My mother said, "Somebody must have come
back."
My mother lost 150 people. She had nine
brothers and sisters. They all had
children. Three years of waiting.
Not one person,
every one of them was murdered.
>> Why did that make you not want to accept
reparations?
>> Because I didn't want it anybody to
think it's a payment for the murder
of all the people. You can't pay for it.
And I was just afraid that somebody
would think that we're accepting the
payments
for the death of our family.
Before negotiations could begin, the
claims conference and the Israeli
government had to be [music] absolutely
sure that Adnau was sincere, that he
would agree to significant reparations,
and that Germany would actually pay.
Goldman's meeting with an hour in London
would be the first time a high-ranking
Jewish person had met with a senior
German official since the end of the
war.
It was a little bit taken out of a John
Le car movie.
Nahung Goldman came through the
deliveries [music] entrance.
Ado was already in the hotel. So it was
all very very secret
because it [music] still was
unbelievable to have negotiation talks
back in that time.
Goldman said a very unusual thing to the
chancellor of an upcoming nation.
He said, "Before you even answer, give
me 15 minutes and don't interrupt me."
>> Goldman laid out the volcanic
controversy about negotiations with
Germany.
>> He said, "If there is to be any
haggling, it would be better not to
begin the talks at all."
He also made very clear that without any
acknowledgement
of the moral dimension
there would never be a negotiation
talks.
And by moral dimension he means that
Adenoa and the whole government has to
again accept unbelievable crimes have
been committed in the responsibility of
Germany.
the fear Nahung Bman had that the whole
German government would regard this to
be good business
>> we're getting something for giving that
reparations
asked for 1 billion
as the basis of negotiations
wrote in his diary that Adenau said this
to him at the conclusion of their me.
Those who know me know that I am [music]
a man of few words and I detest high
flown talk. But I must tell you that
while you were speaking, I felt the
wings of world history beating in this
room.
>> [music]
>> In a meeting of the Israeli Foreign
Ministry, there was a discussion where
to have the negotiations.
Well, first of all, it was clear it
cannot happen in Germany. Germany was
off limits for Jews.
The location was secret because they
were afraid that there might be violent
attacks. So, in the end, they uh decided
to go to a neutral country.
It was very hush hush. I was told get on
a boat and you proceed to the meeting
place wherever it is. I didn't know
where it was.
There was this bomb being sent to Adinoa
and that guy who opened the package
actually died.
We landed in Holland, checked in at the
immigration there. They looked at my
papers and they said, "Wait a moment."
And then the man came out and a big car
and he said, "I'll get in. I'll take you
to the where you're going."
I said, "Hey, can you tell me where
you're taking me?"
said, "You'll see
the Cascal Udasa,
which had been given by the Dutch
government for the purpose of this
meeting."
Well, the three parties that met in
Vasan,
the Federal Republic of [music] Germany
or West Germany, uh the State of Israel
and the Claims Conference, and none of
those organizations even [music] existed
before the war,
and there was no guarantee that the
[music] negotiations would reach a
successful conclusion.
The claims conference set up a
delegation made up of Ben [music]
Ference, Jacob Robinson and Robinson who
were both of them lawyers and it was
headed by Moses Levit.
>> Israel [music] sent its own delegation.
>> Israel had the benefit of a foreign
ministry with professional diplomats.
The claims conference didn't have that
but they were fortunate by having
personalities who had been dealing with
the restoration of Jewish property
rights under the opaces of the American
army. Ben Fence was one of them. Saul
Kagan [music] was another.
Goldman would stay in the wings until he
was needed. The idea was he was the most
important [music] uh person and so he
should be kept back as ammunition.
The Israeli Foreign Ministry were
preparing nearly everything.
How to enter the room
to enter 5 minutes before the German
delegation appears in order not to meet
them beforehand.
Everybody have seen all those movies.
Yeah. If somebody takes a cigarette, the
other one wants to be polite and
stretches his hand out with a lighter
automatically.
They were told, "Don't take lighters
with you." Yeah. In order not well to
establish a situation where you might be
polite,
you are presenting a collective. You are
not presenting yourself.
Everything was choreographed not to come
close to the Germans.
The next question was which language
should we use? This was also a symbolic
question. Is it possible to use the
language of the perpetrators to speak
about this issue?
Inimaginable.
Good afternoon, gentlemen.
On the 27th of September 1951,
the federal chancellor made the
following statement before the
Bundustak.
Unspeakable crimes were committed in the
name of the German people.
This imposes upon us the obligation to
make moral and material amends both as
regard the individual damage which Jews
have suffered and as regard Jewish
property for which there are no longer
individual claimments.
It further hopes that the efforts made
by Germany to remedy the damage done to
the Jewish people will be appreciated
has given proof to our earnest and
sincere desire to render Vid Mahung.
In the morning, the Germans negotiated
with the Israeli delegation.
In the afternoon, they negotiated with
delegation on behalf of the claims
conference.
In the evening, the claims conference
and the Israeli delegations met to
coordinate their strategy.
Obstacle number one, how serious are the
Germans?
We said, "Okay, what are you offering?"
Because if they're ready to pay $2 a
person, this discussion is over.
For example, many of Jews had stocks and
bonds,
and these were all confiscated by the
Nazis,
and they were very valuable.
it was hand and they said, "Look,
there's millions of dollars worth of
stocks there
and the East Germans, they're not paying
you anything, so why should we do
anything?"
Whatever it was that we wanted to put
in,
they would might say,
which means that exceeds our capacity to
pay.
When the Germans said they want an
accounting of [music] how the claims
conference is going to spend the money
to give them receipts and so on, Moses
Levit answered them with great force and
bitterness.
This is none of your damn business. You
created this mess. We're fixing it.
We're trying to rebuild the lives of the
survivors.
Don't expect us to give you accounts.
[snorts]
As head of the relief organization, the
American Jewish Joint Distribution
Committee, Levit was intimately familiar
with the needs of survivors.
Only three years earlier, he had toured
DP camps in Germany and filmed survivors
with his own camera.
During the negotiations, he wrote in his
diary,
"Sick and exhausted,
stayed in bed uninterested in the whole
world and wanted to chuck the whole
thing and go home.
The German negotiators in Vasanar were
taking their cues from Bon and in
particular from finance minister
Schaefer.
Schaefer's attitude toward Vasanar was
increasingly negative.
>> One has to know that in the same time of
the compensation talks we had the
so-called London depth negotiations.
The London debt conference continues
with the United States, the Soviet Union
and England meeting with the new German
government to demand payment for wartime
destruction.
>> We were still talking about the depths
of the German Reich, which was also a
big number.
>> Schaefer was also getting reports from
the head of the German delegation in
London, Herman Ysef [music] Abs. Abs was
a high level financial adviser to
Adenau. He was also a Nazi collaborator.
During the war, he was an executive at
Deutsche Bank, whose job it was to
dispossess Jewish owned companies of
their assets. The US Army had
recommended indicting him for war
crimes, [music] but he was never tried.
Dealing with UPS was a very difficult
issue. It was clear to everyone in the
claims conference and in the Israeli
delegation that they had no choice but
to deal with the Germans as they were,
including those that had been Nazis.
The Germans would have liked to put the
whole issue to London, which would have
meant that the Jewish claims might have
been part of the larger issue of German
depths resulting from the Second World
War.
The German official said, "First we have
to come to a settlement with the rest of
the world and then we can see what we
can do for Israel." And Israel said,
"No, it has to be the reverse. You have
to acknowledge your debt to us because
it is a moral debt and only then can you
settle with the rest of the world.
About 3 weeks in, the atmosphere between
the Jews and the Germans had fought
considerably.
>> So, Conrad Adinoa picked France Bum to
be the chief negotiator in Vasa.
>> France Boom was a very eminent
opposition figure in the time of the
national socialists. He was removed from
his chair being a university professor
in Fryborg. His deputy was Otto Kuster
who had been a judge. He was removed
from the bench by the Nazis because he
was opposed to the new national
socialist laws.
The delegates were completely
astonished. They said, "Well, I thought
we would meet all those persons who
represented the past in quotation mark."
I think for the German delegation, this
was also not such an easy situation. uh
it was also the first encounter with
officials from world jury.
>> Of course there had been this collective
shame and I think this shame was also in
the in the room.
They were making significant progress.
Then suddenly the German delegation
informed Israel in the claims conference
the negotiations in Vasanar could not
continue until the London debt
conference was finished.
This was exactly what those in the
Jewish world who had opposed
negotiations had feared all along.
The Jews would agree to negotiate and
then the Germans would reneg on their
promises.
The Jews would be made to look like
fools in the eyes of the world and worse
yet even in their own eyes.
Burm and Kusta were disgusted by this.
They were shocked that their government
didn't want to move forward with talks
on Jewish claims.
Burm and Kusta [music] resigned.
They said our government is not serious.
So that was really a treasonous hack on
their part
>> because the Israeli government was so
desperate in need of money. A UPS was
trying to get a cheap deal. So he
brought forward an offer to the Israeli
government. It consisted of 100 million
which was far away from the
expectations. The number which had been
on the table so far was 1 billion.
Goldman is here.
Goldman explained to Adnau that you
couldn't go on this way. There couldn't
be what he called horse trading.
It was humiliating for both sides. It
was unreasonable.
>> I don't know. It was under pressure to
achieve some deal. That's the dynamics
[music] of negotiations. At a certain
point you cannot step back without uh
producing a lot of damage and [music]
the damage would have been huge at that
time.
Without a deal with Israel, [music]
Germany would have not been able to
succeed in [music] the international
realm.
Absolute
land
of the of the
An hour overruled his own government
officials and said that there was not
going to be any link between
negotiations on the Jewish claims and
negotiations on German debts and so the
delegation went back to the negotiating
table.
There were big compromises on the part
of both of Israel and the claims
conference.
Israel demanded $1 billion.
It received $750 million in
installments.
The Germans said they didn't have
[music] the money. And so instead of
paying Israel in cash,
Israel would receive commodities and
oil.
The claims conference had originally
demanded a lump sum of $500 million.
Instead of receiving 500 million, they
received $107 million.
Nah, Goldman later explained that the
reason why was that it accepted that
Israel was in desperate need of the
money. So they prioritized Israel over
the claims conference claim.
The claims [music] conference was
negotiating partly for a global payment
that would go to help the Jewish people,
but an even higher priority was to help
Holocaust survivors individually to
receive pensions directly [music]
from Germany that would help them live
out the rest of their lives in dignity.
But there were many people who were not
eligible under the original program.
people who lived behind the Iron
Curtain, [music] uh people who had been
in hiding or in other places that they
weren't eligible.
The view of the organization ultimately
was let's do what we can now and let's
[music] keep fighting for justice.
The night before the signing, Mosha
Sharet arrived in Luxembourg from Israel
and Conrad Adnanau arrived from Bon.
The men were staying in different hotels
and couriers exchanged the speeches that
they had prepared for the next day.
This is from Sheret's speech.
Our memory is still haunted by the
catastrophe inflicted on the Jewish
people by the German Nazi regime in
which two out of every three European
Jews were put to death.
Forgiveness is not possible.
forg.
Fore
[music]
the idea that no forgiveness is possible
for a Roman Catholic that's a virtual
impossibility.
Catholics believe that people are sinful
but that [music] sins can be repaired.
Well, it was clear from midnight on
Arnau didn't accept the half a sentence
about no forgiveness possible.
As a person, he may accept it but not as
a chancellor of Germany. And then they
came to the conclusion, no speeches at
all.
During the choreography of signing the
[music] agreement, both delegation
arrived from different doors. They
entered the room.
Names were whispered, [music]
Mr. X, Mr. Y, and so on so far.
And then silence prevailed in the room
for about 12 and a half minutes.
Agnawa sat in front of the Israeli
foreign minister Mosha Shalet
and both of them signed the accord
between Israel and Germany.
I'm sitting next to Nam Goldman and
right opposes [music] me is Chancellor
Adnau. time comes to sign the contract
forward the claims conference that had
two parts to it. Goldman whipped out his
pen and he tried it. That didn't work.
But I gave a a pen which my wife had
given me when I graduated from Harvard
and I carried it with me throughout the
war. Good luck charm. I give it to
Goldman.
And the treaty was in fact signed with
my pen.
After the signing of the treaty, Adonoa
went to a chapel
and he prayed there.
[music]
After the agreements were signed, Nakam
Gman wrote a
to Conrad Adnau. Even more important
than the financial significance of the
Luxembourg agreement is its moral
significance. It established a
precedent.
According to the agreement, West Germany
promised to pay Israel in goods and
services.
The goods consisted of raw materials,
especially petroleum,
agricultural produce, industrial
machinery,
ships for the Israeli Navy, and so on.
This agreement first of all upgraded
Israel's standard of living.
It enabled construction of housing and
lodging for the newcomers
with an economic growth around 10 or 11%
peranom.
It was also a sea change.
It broke many taboos.
In
>> those days the country was almost on the
verge of civil war.
What is amazing is that once the
agreement between Israel government and
Germany was signed and the reparations
money had start flowing into Israel,
everybody was happy with it. The
opposition stopped fighting it
>> and the German reparations
rescue the Jewish state. Ironically as
[music] it sound,
>> there's no question that the payments to
the state of Israel were an unqualified
success.
>> As for the individual payments to
survivors,
it's more complicated. Fore!
Foreign! Foreign!
Fore
city.
for
the
Fore!
Foreign! Foreign!
for [music]
the city. [music]
Fore.
Blood bunny. I always called it blood
money.
But I took it because people say you're
stupid. You're stupid. You have such
stupid ideas. Take it. Take it because
they owe it to you.
It was very difficult to accept
reparations.
Personally, I felt that for murdering my
whole family,
that was a very small price to pay
and that we should take [music] the
money.
When I first heard about reparation,
I was living in Brooklyn, New York with
[music] the host family and yes, with my
sister.
My mother's sister Roi was the one who
really really needed the money. She was
genuinely [music] ill.
My whole life in Avitz was guided by the
fact that I was with Roi. I felt that I
belonged to someone who was strong and
will take care of me as a mother would.
Rosie applied. She said that she had the
tattoo on her arm and that her family
was [music] destroyed.
And then she also told them basic facts
that her health was very badly affected.
[music]
But she would say nothing about her
mental state.
She would not open her her soul to the
German doctor.
The doctor told her that the physical
conditions she could have acquired after
being liberated from Ashitz.
Restitution [music] was denied.
I felt a lot like Rosie that I don't
want your money. But I did take it
because I was a young girl. I was able
to go to school because I had that
money.
We [music] needed basic things, you
know, clothes, shoes.
So, this was the only money that we
really had to live on.
Many of the survivors, [music]
they all felt that they didn't get
enough. And they were right.
But the amounts to quite a bit.
There were from the beginning different
perceptions from the German side and the
Jewish side about what lies behind these
agreements. From the German side, this
was what they called Vidor Gut Mah to
make whole. We don't use that term
because we don't think it's possible to
make whole a Holocaust survivor who's
been through the unimaginable.
We call it compensation, recognition,
and acknowledgement. important, but this
doesn't make whole.
>> We don't have the right to forgive.
Germany is a very important ally of
Israel today and a very close friend,
but it does not erase the past in any
way.
for
the Germans mistakenly thought that the
Luxembourg agreement ments were the
beginning and the end of all
negotiations on reparations.
And in fact, this was just the first
round of many, many more rounds of
negotiations. [music]
When the program first started, those
programs provided a quite limited subset
of survivors. And what the job of the
claims conference has been ever since is
to broaden and expand the eligibility.
Fore.
[music]
Ultimately, these negotiations are not
over just money or even individuals.
They're negotiations [music] over
history itself.
What happened and how Germany and we as
a society understand that [music]
history
and acknowledge that history.
This was a reckoning.
The first reparations ever paid by a
state to individuals the state had
harmed.
An honest confrontation with your past
is the most important way in which you
can build a different future.
We have
the
[music]
Deutseland.
Well, Schult is for Fore.
People ask me, "When will this stop?"
It's our obligation to make sure that we
never stop
so that we continue to [music] provide
dignity.
We continue to provide needed
assistance.
The compensation is not just dollars.
It's a statement that they have not been
forgotten.
I hope Luxembourg was a stepping stone
toward a more humane and peaceful world.
It illustrated the determination of
human beings to [music] survive and to
carry on.
>> My mother [music] was a concert pianist.
I grew up with music.
Dancing
helped me get [music] back my sanity.
When I dance, I forget [music]
everything.
I see only [music] beauty and I hear
only beauty.
>> [music]
[music]